{"tossups": [{"question": "A 1971 Supreme Court case named for opposing parties with this surname ruled against differential treatment based on sex. The U.S. representative for New York's 23rd congressional district who replaced Eric Massa in 2010 has this surname. A Speaker of the House with this surname stopped the \"disappearing quorum\" tactic by counting all members as present even if they ignored the roll call. For ten points, give this surname of U.S. politician Thomas Brackett, sometimes referred to as \"Czar.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Reed</u></b> (accept <em><b><u>Reed</u></b> v. Reed</em>; accept Tom <b><u>Reed</u></b>; accept Thomas Brackett <b><u>Reed</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Charles Colson once suggested that this organization should be attacked in a firebombing. This organization\u2019s first president, Harry Moulton, organized a movement against FDR\u2019s National Recovery Act. This organization was founded by the merger of three organizations including its namesake\u2019s graduate school, which was linked to Washington University of St. Louis. Haim Saban previously was the namesake of this organization's Center of Middle Eastern Policy. For ten points, name this think tank, seen as the American Enterprise Institute's left-leaning counterpart.", "answer": "The <b><u>Brookings</u></b> Institution", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man translated the First Helvetic Confession into English and served as a bodyguard in defense of George Wisehart. This man considered kneeling during communion idolatrous, leading to the Black Rubric. French forces under Leone Strozzi [[leh-OH-neh STROH-tsee]] captured this man and turned him into a galley slave. This man wrote the five-volume tome <em>The History of the Reformation in Scotland</em>. This man wrote a \"first blast of a trumpet\" criticizing the unnatural \"monstrous regiment of women,\" targeting Mary I of England. For ten points, name this Scottish reformer, the founder of Presbyterianism.", "answer": "John <b><u>Knox</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man claimed that like that of the \u201cwhite man,\" the heart of a slave \u201cswells with love... [and] aches with sorrow\u201d in a legal brief written during the <em>Creole</em> case. This man succeeded Leroy Walker in one post and used his experience as a lawyer in New Orleans to serve as Attorney General under Jefferson Davis. Strategies for dealing with the Union blockade were brainstormed by this man, who was named after a relative who oversaw his <em>brit milah</em> ceremony. For ten points, name this Confederate Secretary of State, a politician of Jewish descent.", "answer": "Judah P(hilip) <b><u>Benjamin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During a conflict with police, one leader of this country said, \u201cIf you want to kill the president, here he is, kill him if you have the guts.\" This country faced 2019 anti-austerity demonstrations at Carondelet [[kah-ROHN-deh-let]] Palace and a raid on Pichincha [[pee-CHEEN-chah]] Universal. Julian Assange was granted asylum in an embassy of this country, which elected the Guillermo Lasso as president in 2021. For ten points, name this South American country which faced 2015 inheritance tax protests against the Alianza Pa\u00eds [[pah-YEES]].", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ecuador</u></b> (accept Rep\u00fablica del <b><u>Ecuador</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A royal huntsman was the dedicatee of a painting by this artist which depicts the competition between Arachne [[ah-RAHK-nee]] and Athena. A Flemish artist's painting of the Hungarian king, Ferdinand IV, may have inspired one of this artist\u2019s paintings of a \u201chumane captain.\u201d A checkered flag and lances feature in that work by this artist paying homage to Ambrogio [[ahm-BROH-zhoh]] Spinola. A painting featuring an <em>Infanta</em>, a dog, and two people with dwarfism was completed by this man for Philip IV. For ten points, name this artist of <em>The Surrender of Breda</em> and <em>Las Meninas</em>.", "answer": "Diego <b><u>Vel\u00e1zquez</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This battle included Operation Scotland II [[TWO]], and it ended in the termination of the McNamara Line. A combined force lifted the siege at this battle via Operation Pegasus. Operation Niagara was launched during this battle, at which William Westmoreland planned to use nuclear weapons. This battle followed the Hill Fights and the Battle of Dak To [[DAHK TOH]]. For ten points, name this 1968 Vietnam War battle in which a besieged American force avoided losing to the North Vietnamese in Qu\u1ea3ng Tr\u1ecb [[KWAHNG TREE]] Province.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Khe Sanh</u></b> [[KEH-SAHN]]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One ruler with this first name captured a castle at Mold after a prince\u2019s defeat at the hands of the Earl of Essex. A skirmish at Cilmeri [[kil-MEH-dee]] led to the death of another man with this first name, who was married to Eleanor Montfort. That man with this first name was forced to accept limits on his domain in the Treaty of Aberconwy, which stabilized his territory in Gwynedd [[GWIN-eth]]. Though not Scottish, Edward Longshanks carried out a campaign against a ruler of this name often known \u201cthe Last\u201d or ap Gruffydd [[GRIF-ith]]. For ten points, give this name shared by several Welsh rulers.", "answer": "<b><u>Llywelyn</u></b> (accept <b><u>Llywelyn</u></b> the Great, <b><u>Llywelyn</u></b> mab Iorwerth, <b><u>Llywelyn</u></b> ap Gruffufdd, or <b><u>Llywelyn</u></b> the Last)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After this man's trial, Judge William Johnson wrote a letter questioning the trial's fairness. Joe LaRoche and George Wilson, as well as Peter Prioleau [[pree-oh-LOH]], betrayed this man, leading to the deployment of an armed force under James Hamilton. This man earned his independence after winning the lottery, marrying a woman named Beck, and founding the \"Bethel circuit.\" This man planned an event for Bastille Day, after which he intended to sail to Haiti. For ten points, name this man who led a failed 1822 slave revolt in Charleston.", "answer": "Denmark <b><u>Vesey</u></b> (accept <b><u>Telemaque</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At this battle, Titus Statilius Taurus, the last man to hold multiple consulships, received the surrender of his opponent's land forces. The use of Liburnian vessels and the defection of Quintus Dellius helped one side win this battle. Marcus Agrippa fought in this battle against Lucius Gellius Polico and Gaius Sosius. The city of Nicopolis was founded after this battle, which took place in the Ambracian Gulf. After this battle, a ruler took the name Augustus. For ten points, name this 31 BC naval battle near Greece in which Cleopatra and Mark Antony lost to Octavian.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Actium</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This law may be legally circumvented using the Noerr-Pennington Doctrine and the Parker immunity doctrine of state sovereignty. Alan Greenspan claimed this law killed many products and inventions. An Ohio senator names this law which deals with violations that are \"per se\" and of the \"rule of reason.\" This law, which was modified by the Clayton Act, was used against Northern Securities Company and Standard Oil, among other monopolies. For ten points, name this 1890 antitrust act.", "answer": "<b><u>Sherman</u></b> Antitrust Act of 1890", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One man claimed that the location for this meeting was chosen because \u201cnone of the big powers would be offended.\u201d During this meeting, one leader asked another if he was willing to \"turn down a historic opportunity because of a single word.\" One side at this meeting called for the restriction of SDI research to laboratories, which contributed to the breakdown of negotiations. This meeting led to the signing of the Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty a year later in 1987. For ten points, name this summit between Mikhail Gorbachev and Ronald Reagan.", "answer": "<b><u>Reykjav\u00edk</u></b> Summit", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "John C. Taylor bought this man's work as part of the Ordway-Rand collection. Special end tables were named for this man's \"Stands,\" which featured cast iron bases and an extendible pipe leg. Levin Corbin Handy took over this man's business, which had a studio at 359 Broadway. William Page trained this man, who created the <em>Gallery of</em> <em>Illustrious Americans</em>. Alexander Gardner and Timothy O'Sullivan worked as assistants for this man, who produced works like <em>The Dead of Antietam</em>. For ten points, name this Civil War photographer.", "answer": "Mathew <b><u>Brady</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The title of this film based on a Humphrey Cobb novel comes from Thomas Gray's \"Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard.\" This film received criticism from the French military, which objected to its portrayal of their organization. This 1957 film is based on a true story of four French soldiers who were executed as an example to other troops. While not as well-known as <em>Dr. Strangelove</em>, many consider this to be Stanley Kubrick's greatest film. For ten points, name this anti-war film set during World War One and starring Kirk Douglas as Colonel Dax.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Paths of Glory</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {"question": "This woman helped oversee the creation of the Rapidan Camp, which was a precursor to Camp David. This woman helped create the first English translation of the Latin text <em>De Re Metallica</em>. While her husband was a cabinet member, this woman served as president of the Girl Scouts of the USA. This student of Mandarin travelled extensively with her husband while he worked as a mining engineer. This woman was the only female geology major during her time at Stanford, where she met her husband. For ten points, name this First Lady during the presidency of FDR\u2019s predecessor.", "answer": "<b><u>L</u></b>ou <b><u>Hoover</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Along with the Hanbo scandal, this event contributed to serious economic issues for South Korea. This event resulted in the collapse of Finance One, the largest finance company of the country in which it originated. This event was a significant cause of Suharto's fall from power, due to the rupiah being drastically devalued. For ten points, name this 1997 event which started with the collapse of the Thai baht, triggering capital flight and a major market slump in countries including Indonesia and Malaysia.", "answer": "1997 <b><u>Asian Financial</u> </b> Crisis (accept <b><u>Tom Yum Koong</u></b> crisis)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man wrote his own epitaph which read, \u201cNo friend ever served me, and no enemy ever wronged me, whom I have not repaid in full.\u201d In the Campanian town of Nola, this man received the Grass Crown for his defeat of various Italic tribes in the Social War. The Sack of Athens was overseen by this man, who ordered mass executions of members of the <em>equites</em> [[EH-kwee-tehs]]. This man led a coup that was enabled by his rival\u2019s military reforms which gave generals stronger control of their armies. For ten points, name this rival of Gaius Marius who revived the office of dictator in the late Roman Republic.", "answer": "Lucius Cornelius <b><u>Sulla</u></b> Felix", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Charles Diggs was the first chairman of this group which, in 2006, rejected Steve Cohen\u2019s application to join it. Chaired by Karen Bass, this organization was founded by thirteen individuals including John Conyers. In 2011, Allen West became the first Republican member of this organization in fourteen years. In 2020, clothing made of kente cloth was handed out by members of this group to those House members observing 8 minutes and 46 seconds of silence. For ten points, name this caucus consisting entirely of African-Americans.", "answer": "<b><u>Congressional Black</u></b> Caucus (or <b><u>CBC</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Melissus commanded the forces of this island in a conflict with a major city-</u><u>state. One of the earliest tunnels with two openings was this island's Eupalinian</u></b> <b><u>[[yoo-pah-LIN-ee-an]] aqueduct. On this island a road that crossed over the Imbrasos</u></b> <b><u>River came to be known as the (+)</u> Sacred Way and linked to a temple dedicated to the goddess Hera. The idea that mathematical equations govern planetary motion was proposed by a native of this island who found a way to calculate the (*) </b>hypotenuse length in a right triangle. For ten points, name this Greek island on which Pythagoras was born.", "answer": "<b><u>Samos</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Debby Applegate won a Pulitzer Prize for a biography of this man titled</u> </b><em><b><u>The</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Most Famous Man in America</u></b></em><b><u>. A confession that was reported to Elizabeth Cady</u></b> <b><u>Stanton resulted in a court case that challenged this man\u2019s denouncement of free (+)</u></b> <b>love. That widely reported trial dealt with this man\u2019s affair with Elizabeth Tilton. Sharps manufactured a set of weapons sent to abolitionists in (*) </b>Kansas that became known as this man\u2019s namesake \"Bibles.\" For ten points, name this abolitionist orator who was the brother of the author of <em>Uncle Tom\u2019s Cabin</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Henry</u></b> Ward <b><u>Beecher</u></b> (prompt on \"Beecher\" or \"Harriet Beecher Stowe\" after \"Uncle Tom's Cabin\" is mentioned; accept <b><u>Beecher</u></b>'s Bibles before \"Uncle Tom's Cabin\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1321, the poet Dante died in exile in this city. Roman empress consort Galla</u></b> <b><u>Placidia [[GAH-luh plah-KID-ee-uh]] lent her name to a famous mausoleum in this</u></b> <b><u>city, one of many monuments contributing to this city's namesake UNESCO World</u></b> <b><u>Heritage Site. This city served as the capital of the (+)</u> Ostrogothic kingdom until it was reconquered by the Byzantines in 540 AD, after which its Basilica of San Vitale [[vee-TAH-leh]] became home to a mosaic of (*) </b>Justinian and Theodora. For ten points, name this city in the Emilia-Romagna region of modern Italy.", "answer": "<b><u>Ravenna</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Nicolas Bergasse [[behr-GAHS]] was a student of this man and systematized</u></b> <b><u>his teachings. Francisca Osterlin was the subject of a treatment by this man who</u></b> <b><u>created an \u201cartificial tide\u201d which involved the ingestion of an iron mixture. That</u></b> <b><u>technique by this man was investigated by a (+)</u> Louis XVI-appointed commission which included Benjamin Franklin and relied on the belief that one, all-encompassing fluid could influence and heal people. This man dubbed that pseudoscientific force (*) </b>\u201canimal magnetism.\" For ten points, name this German doctor whose theory has become synonymous with \"hypnosis.\"", "answer": "Franz <b><u>Mesmer</u></b> (accept <b><u>Mesmer</u></b>ism; accept <b><u>Mesmer</u></b>ize)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "<b><u>Viola Spolin taught improvisation lessons at this place, where a music school</u></b> <b><u>was founded by Eleanor Sophia Smith. This location served the Greek Delta and Little</u></b> <b><u>Italy and included medical professional Alice Hamilton. Wallace (+)</u> Kirkland photographed children at this location where the Great Ladies of Halsted Street created the Little Theatre Movement. Ellen Gates (*) </b>Starr co-founded this location, whose other founder was inspired by London's Toynbee Hall. For ten points, name this settlement house in Chicago co-founded by Jane Addams.", "answer": "<b><u>Hull</u></b> House", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Prior to this battle, William Bliss responded to a demand for surrender by</u></b> <b><u>stating \"I beg leave to say that I decline acceding to your request.\u201d One side</u></b> <b><u>unknowingly selected George Washington\u2019s birthday as the date of this battle, which</u></b> <b><u>boosted the morale of the (+)</u> American side. Occurring near Saltillo [[sal-TEE-yo]], this battle is sometimes alternatively named for a site translating to \u201cthe narrow place,\u201d or La (*) </b>Angostura. For ten points, name this victory for Zachary Taylor in the Northern theatre of the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Buena Vista</u></b> (accept Battle of <b><u>La Angostura</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man arranged for a publication by Benjamin Martyn \"to the Trustees\" of</u></b> <b><u>one colony to appear in several newspapers. William Stephens and Henry Parker</u></b> <b><u>succeeded this man as governor. This man attacked Thomas Bambridge, the warden</u></b> <b><u>of Fleet (+)</u> Prison, as the head of the Gaols [[JAILS]] Committee. This man banned rum and slavery in his colony and focused the economy on wine and silk. This man defeated a Spanish invasion at the Battle of (*) </b>Bloody Marsh. Establishing a colony as a debtors' haven, for ten points, what planner of Savannah founded the colony of Georgia?", "answer": "James <b><u>Oglethorpe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Stuart Manley re-popularized this five-word phrase after finding an original</u></b> <b><u>document containing it while sorting through used books. Originally part of the</u></b> <b><u>\u201cHome Publicity\u201d program, this phrase is often conflated with a national attitude</u></b> <b><u>typified by the (+)</u> \u201cstiff upper lip.\u201d During an imitation that became popular during the COVID-19 pandemic, the second part of this phrase is replaced with \u201cwash your hands.\u201d Often written below a (*) </b>Tudor crown on motivational posters since 1939, for ten points, what phrase was originally created to urge Brits to not panic during the Second World War?", "answer": "<b><u>\"Keep Calm and Carry On\"</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A 171-day long assembly during the reign of this monarch became known as</u></b> <b><u>the \"Longest Legislature.\" John Owen Dominis served as prince consort during the</u></b> <b><u>reign of this monarch, who was opposed by a non-French Committee of Safety. A</u></b> <b><u>group including (+)</u> Lorrin Thurston opposed this monarch\u2019s attempts to reform the 1887 Bayonet Constitution. (*) </b>Sanford Dole helped to overthrow this monarch, who ruled from Iolani Palace. The song \"Aloha 'Oe\" was written by, for ten points, what queen of Hawaii?", "answer": "<b><u>Lili\u02bbuokalani</u></b> (accept Lydia Lili\u02bbu Loloku Walania <b><u>Kamaka\u02bbeha</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}